A Guide to the Papers of the Stuart Family
Special Collections, Kegley Library, Wytheville Community College
- Correspondence April - July 1864
  - James Ward Stuart, camp near Petersburg, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 12 July 1864. (Box-folder 1:5)
    4 p. Re: ill health of their mother, request to take their mother to Dr. Seldon or Dr. Moore, the Petersburg campaign -- "I think the present campaign will end the war & I hope to return," description of trenches and line of defense, and his illness of diarrhea.
  - William A. Hart, camp near Petersburg, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 21 July 1864. (Box-folder 1:5)
    2 p. Re: hospitalization of James Ward Stuart for diarrhea.
- Correspondence August - September 1864
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion Magnetic Furnace, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 14 August 1864. (Box-folder 1:6)
    4 p. Re: death of her mother Margaret McCutcheon Hay Ward Stuart, and request for her answer to his proposal of marriage.
  - Charles Benton Thomas to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 30 August 1864. (Box-folder 1:6)
    4 p. Re: her acceptance of his proposal of marriage, his displeasure at her insisting to postpone the marriage, planned marriage of his sister Virginia Ann Thomas to Dr. John Davis Carter, and his hopes for marriage before Christmas.
  - James Ward Stuart, in the trenches, Otey Battalion, 13th Va. Battalion Artillery, Longstreet's Camp, Petersburg to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 29 September 1864. (Box-folder 1:6)
    2 p. Re: his trouble finding his camp in Petersburg, mentions Waldo W. Walton, work digging trenches, poor chances for an early engagement with the enemy, collection of debts and payments from Charles Crockett, James Brown, and request for her to send by Henry Crockett the overcoat of William Stuart.
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Bachelor's Headquarters, Marion Magnetic Furnace, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 29 September 1864. (Box-folder 1:6)
    3 p. Re: reported movement of Federal forces towards Saltville, and his entreaties for her to marry him sooner.
  - William Stuart, Waynesboro, Augusta County, Virginia to Jane Stuart and Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 20 September 1864. (Box-folder 1:6)
    2 p. [faded and torn]. Re: battle of Fisher's Hill, and capture of George Hanson and Harold Mathews by Federal troops.
- Correspondence October 1864
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion Magnetic Furnace, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 1 October 1864. (Box-folder 1:7)
    4 p. Re: his orders from Gen. Echols to return his men to work at the furnace since it is in blast, advancement of Federal forces, and his dismay at her postponement of their wedding.
  - James Ward Stuart, camp near Petersburg, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 7 October 1864. (Box-folder 1:7)
    2 p. [faded]. Re: life in the trenches and lines around Petersburg, request for information of battle at Saltville, reports of reinforcements to Grant's army, and requests her to hire out the "negroes ... before they eat you out of house & home."
  - William Stuart, New Market, Rockingham County, Virginia to Laura Stuart and Jane Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 21 October 1864. (Box-folder 1:7)
    4 p. Re: detailed description of battle of Cedar Creek, Virginia [19 October 1864], secondary skirmish at Fisher's Hill, casualties of the 4th Virginia Infantry Regiment, and his nighttime escape from capture by Federal forces.
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion Magnetic Furnace, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 29 October 1864. (Box-folder 1:7)
    1 p. Re: his dismay at her not writing to him.
  - James Ward Stuart, trenches, Petersburg, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 31 October 1864. (Box-folder 1:7)
    4 p. Re: daily occupation of digging trenches, description of life in the trenches including food and cooking, description of artillery and infantry armament, "detailed" men being put into ranks, Fort Gregg "2 1/2 miles to our right," health of "Mammy," inquiry about "Miss Marion," hiring of slave Alex to Mr. John Buchanan, and his slave Charles cooking for the soldiers.
  - William Stuart, camp at New Market, Virginia to Laura Stuart and Jane Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 31 October 1864. (Box-folder 1:7)
    4 p. Re: chastisement for lack of communication, and their bad writing and spelling.
- Correspondence November - December 1864
  - James Ward Stuart, camp 4 miles of S. W. of Petersburg, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 11 November 1864. (Box-folder 1:8)
    2 p. Re: bad weather, battalion being placed in reserve, wounding of Thomas M. Fendley, Onslow B. Sims, John William Haney, and Henry C. Slaymaker, nighttime alarms in the trenches, and requests that she hire out slave Martha "at once."
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Headquarters Bachelor's Division, Marion Magnetic Furnace, Smyth County, Virginia] to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 28 November 1864. (Box-folder 1:8)
    4 p. Re: a "grave charge against your fidelity," visit of Rev. J. T. Leftwich, deer hunting, Rev. Leftwich's wife -- "I do really think he does glory more in the golden chains as he calls them by which he is bound up by that little Yankee wife of his then any man I ever saw," and his continued dismay at the postponement of their wedding.
  - James Ward Stuart, Camp Walker, 4 miles S. W. of Petersburg, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 29 November 1864. (Box-folder 1:8)
    4 p. Re: duties of cleaning camp, building winter huts, digging wells, inquiry about return of his slave Charles to Wytheville, his cooking duties, his request for Mr. Paulett to send him two bushels of beans, and request for her to send potatoes, apples, onions, molasses, red peppers, apple butter and beans. He also inquires about hiring out of slave Martha, payment of tax-in-kind, date of slave Mammy's death, hiring of slave Alex to Jno. Buchanan, and reason for postponement of wedding to Charles Benton Thomas.
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion Magnetic Furnace, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 7 December 1864. (Box-folder 1:8)
    4 p. Re: his missing her, his continued dismay over postponement of wedding, and his admonishment for her not to show "partiality to other young gentlemen after I gave you such a good lecturing about it."
- Correspondence January - April 1865
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Mountain View, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 15 January 1865. (Box-folder 1:9)
    3 p. Re: her role as his guardian angel, and visit to cousin Vic [Victoria Apperson Hull] and Pauline Hull and their knowledge of the engagement.
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Mountain View, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 22 January 1865. (Box-folder 1:9)
    3 p. Re: assurance that she will come to love him "I don't think I have ever yet failed to gain the affectionate regard of any worthy person with whom I have long associated."
  - Waldo W. Walton, Fort Gregg, near Petersburg, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 22 February 1865. (Box-folder 1:9)
    3 p. Re: mentions possibility of J. Williamson McGavock joining battalion -- "I hope he will succeed I want him down here so I can take care of him," return of William A. Slaymaker to duty, Henry C. Slaymaker in Wilmington, N. C., and marriage of Mary Sanders.
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion Magnetic Furnace, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 3 March 1865. (Box-folder 1:9)
    2 p. Re: plans for wedding on 15 March 1865, and location of Rev. Leftwich.
  - James Ward Stuart, Camp Pegram, Virginia to Laura Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia. 13 March 1865. (Box-folder 1:9)
    2 p. Re: marriage of William Stuart and Nannie Hancock, approval of admittance of J. Williamson McGavock into battalion, and state of war "it seems to me this campaign must end the war on way or the other."
  - William Stuart, Camp Ewell, Petersburg, Virginia to [Jane Stuart], Wytheville, Virginia.. 16 March 1865. (Box-folder 1:9)
    3 p. [faded]. Re: mentions Nannie Hancock, and correction of her belief that battalion will go to North Carolina.
  - William Stuart, in the trenches immediately in front of Petersburg, Virginia to [Jane Stuart], Wytheville, Virginia. 19 March 1865. (Box-folder 1:9)
    2 p. Re: location of James Ward Stuart near Burgess Mill on the Boydton Plank Road, and request for her to attend to his business.
  - Jane Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, Smyth County, Virginia. 21 April 1865. (Box-folder 1:9)
    2 p. Re: health of William Stuart who returned from Mt. Airy and request to send Alf to the depot to pick her up.
- Correspondence June - December 1865
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Mountain View, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, Wytheville, Virginia. 11 June 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. Re: working on mill, her more "judicious" love for him, mentions Mr. Benham, Jim Byars, and Virginia Ann Thomas Carter and Dr. John Davis Carter.
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Smyth County, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, Wytheville, Virginia. 24 September 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    4 p. Re: construction of tannery near Marion in Smyth County, successful business trip of Abijah Thomas in New York City, "he thinks that the leather business will be very profitable," sale of his iron, plans to buy house in Marion, property of George Venable for sale for $2,000, thoughts of going in to business with Scott Staley, and extraction of her tooth.
  - William Stuart, Mount Airy, Virginia to "Ollie & Benton" [Laura Stuart Thomas and Charles Benton Thomas], Marion, Virginia. 2 November 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    3 p. [faded]. Re: encouragement to shop at his store, Mr. Paulett, and Minerva Margaret Buchanan.
  - Jane Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, Marion, Virginia. 11 November 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. Re: chastisement for not writing her, plans to rent out the family house, her plans to board with the buyer, departure of her cook Rose, and visit of Mr. Lacy.
  - William Stuart, Mount Airy, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, Marion, Virginia. 17 November 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. Re: news of his family - "My family are well & getting along very well & don't fight hardly any. Hope you & your man have quit fighting," trip of James Ward Stuart to the northern states, former cook Rose working for Bob Preston at the "Depot," and Waldo W. Walton. NOTE: on the reverse of this letter is another letter written by Waldo W. Walton.
  - Waldo W. Walton, Mt. Airy, Virginia to [Laura Stuart Thomas?]. 10 Nov. 1871. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. Re: trip of William Stuart and himself to visit.
  - Jane Stuart, Wytheville, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, Marion, Virginia. 31 November 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. Re: her illness of cough and cold, treatment of her by Mrs. Spiller with morphine, her praise of Mrs. Spiller -- "I think Mrs. Spiller a much better Dr. than her distinguished brother. I showed her the medicine I had been taken which he sent me & she advised me to take no more of it."
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, Wytheville, Virginia. 11 December 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. Re: illness of Priscilla Scott Thomas, death and funeral of "Uncle Edward" [possibly Edward A. Scott], furniture for their house, property in Alexandria [probably the Mount Vernon Cotton Factory] -- "I have no confidence whatever with the success of the enterprise," and his father [Abijah Thomas] giving him "a start at the tannery & then turn the entire management of it over to me."
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas [Wytheville, Virginia.] 18 December 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    4 p. Re: health of infant nephew Thomas Martin Carter [son of Virginia Ann Thomas Carter and John Davis Carter], visit of Colonel Carter, construction work on their house, his desire to enter business partnership with James Ward Stuart, his wish that she join the church, possibility of Lucy [unknown] to work for them, hiring of former slave Sam [unknown] for work at tannery "I could give him the same wages I am giving the common white laborer in my employment," and good conditions for employees in shoe factory of Galahan [Gollehon].
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, Wytheville, Virginia. 20 December 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. Re: completion of construction of their house, and work at tannery.
  - Charles Benton Thomas, Marion, Virginia to Laura Stuart Thomas, [Wytheville, Virginia. 23 December 1865. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. [fragment] Re: sawing shingles for house, work on portico, butchering of hogs, inquiry about her plans to move into new house, and inquiry about hiring of former slaves Lucy, Fount, and Sam, and Mose White a former servant of Oral Sprinkle.
  - [unknown] to Jane Stuart and Laura Stuart Thomas [unknown]. N.d. (Box-folder 1:10)
    2 p. Re: baby of Laura Stuart Thomas [George Stuart Thomas], spread of whooping cough among children in town, and Tom [unknown] and Wesley Paulett.